welcome to the sixth episode of under
the hood so in in some of the previous
episode you might have seen we talked
about um we talked about different
things we talked about AI we talked
about the compiler we talked a lot about
performance and how to write performance
a code uh but today I have G with me hi
g hi and we are to talk about our app
our BAS app and uh also about events and
caponization and all these things right
um so welcome g g um please introduce
yourself so you you've been working with
uh you're primary on the appside for a
while uh so what what what are you doing
you know what is your what is your role
in the in the engineering team so I'm an
uh I'm an architect on the application
team and uh currently mainly focused on
extensibility and componentization
of the
application um as well as other
architecture related things related to
the application all right cool so so you
know the app very well it's fair to say
I hope so yeah yeah so so before we talk
about compiz and event and all this
let's go a little bit back in time uh we
didn't always have uh events as a
customization mechanism we'll talk a lot
more about event later but um in in the
earlier versions of bcn Na if you wanted
to extend a the the approach was
different yeah so before extensions we
are we had a code customization model so
our code is I guess semiopen Source um
yes so mean we ship the code yeah we
ship the code to to all our partners um
it's not open source because it's not
open to the public but it's open to our
partners and um the way they extended
the application was by changing the
source code that we Shi to them so just
just change the line of code and just
just go in add code change code remove
code uh up to them whatever they needed
to to build their their features on top
of ours that was the so so that's the
code that's what we call refer to as
code customization approach right yes
and uh so we as as early I think as 20
2016 yeah we stting introducing events
as another as an alternative
customization mechanism right so why why
is cod why did want to get away uh from
code customization why why not stick
with it and just proceed right so code
customization was a very successful
model because it was very flexible but
it had a a big downside in that whenever
we changed the code and we shipped a new
version or you wanted to you had to code
customize across different
localizations then you had to merge um
the original code with the modified code
so our partners uh spent a lot of time
uh merging text basically in these text
uh to merge their changes into our new
code or to merge their changes into a
different localization and that's that's
an expensive uh part of the code
customization process
so in I think 2016 Version 9 we
introduced um events uh we had two types
of events so crud events um they're like
platform raised events when you modify a
record or when you open a page and
integration events um so integration
events were a way of taking the code
customization out of the source code so
you would subscribe to this event which
was placed where you wanted to put your
code and then when you know you didn't
have this merge problem anymore so that
that was the the goal so one of the
motivation also was you at that time we
were actually going to the cloud right
yeah so I think this was early in our
journey to the cloud um the merge model
the the merging code and the old code
customization is not really fitted for
the cloud right yeah so it's the when we
go to the cloud uh um upgrades become a
very different Beast right so before all
the upgrades were on Prem managed by a
partner who went in and did code merges
and then they had a two-step data
upgrade whereas in the cloud upgrades
are expected to be much more frequent
but also kind of instant uh and
automatic and also you know major
difference is that in the past partners
would take care of these upgrades yeah
and I moved to the cloud that we had to
take care of so in order to scale we had
to find another way to uh to for
extensibility right y y it's also a
shift in uh going from a bespoke
solution for a given customer to a much
more repeatable solution where Partners
can sell the same feature to many
different customers without having to do
all this merging work and and all this
yeah so we move to so that's the
extension model we move from a code
based customization code sorry code
customization uh to um to to extensions
which are basically a piece of code
which is on top of the the Bas app or
the app we ship right so at the
beginning in in our in our app in the
code we ship for ma there was no event
at all so we you know when we started
with that so we had to introduce this
event somehow yeah uh so what's what
what's the process for that but how how
did we go about that yeah so uh there's
been different stages
um so the very first events we we
introduced um the very first usage of
events was for the the workflow feature
which we were building at the time so
that we uh when we were developing the
workflow feature we put events where we
needed them for that feature at the same
time we also introduced I think it was
around 300 events with in the most
commonly extended places so think sales
post Journal L posting sales posting and
those were very highly curated events
like we knew that those places were
heavily customized so that they they
would get great usage um but they you
know ultimately 300 is a drop in the
bucket right so it's very little so in
order to um get the events that that
Partners needed um we ask them uh we you
know which event where do you need an
event which events do you need and we
did that by um getting them to to
request events on GitHub so GitHub
issues um and so we got over the years
thousands of of requests where Partners
needed to inject their code into ours um
so actually most events that are in the
in in the code today are have been
requested by by Partners right yeah as
opposed to if if you should compare the
ones that we introduced Microsoft
introduced and the one that have been
requested originally by Partners yeah
I'd say over 90% is partner
requested so we had this yeah so we had
this basically Community Driven approach
in terms of um how you know how we made
this our app extensible right so how
many how many events do we have today
total right uh show you a slide that
shows uh little bit about the the
history of how these events uh came
about out so we started in Version 9 we
had no events we added a couple of for
workflow and MH then uh there were like
10 events or remember it's hard I think
in the first version we shipped like 300
events okay so so we we shipped a pretty
large number of events in that was good
so right now in version
25 I think we have
22,500 events mhm um and in the in the
first few years the the uh growth
was uh almost exponential but then it it
flattened out so since version 15 I
think we have linear growth we had but
we're still adding events we're still
adding events and as far as I can tell
we haven't slowed down yet okay so um
yeah we Partners need a lot of events we
add a lot of these events and uh do you
think we have too many
events personally yeah I think we have
way too many events um so I have another
slide that I can show that maybe
explains a little bit about uh why
so we have
22,500 events and for uh our Cloud
platform we can we can check how many of
these events are used by how many apps
and how many environments so looking at
our usage Telemetry yeah looking at our
usage Telemetry so we have about
3,400 events that are not used at all in
the class
nobody nobody we could remove them
nobody would
notice unless unless some on but in the
cloud nobody would notice okay um then
you look at events that are used uh by
single environment so there's there's
one customer out there that uses this
event that's another 5600 events MH and
then uh as you as you look at how many
events are used more and more so uh 53%
of events
so that's 11,000 something events I
think my math is right uh are used in
less than 100
environments so 100 environments to our
Cloud environment is is really almost
nothing um and then if you look at under
a thousand environments where you know
it becomes a significant number we're at
85% okay so the large majority of events
are used by very few people mhm um
there's also another uh statistic which
is interesting uh is that most of our
code doesn't have integration events at
all at all so I think the reason we're
still seeing event requests is because
we have room to grow m not in every
object so so what you're saying is that
a lot of the events are concentrated
actually on few objects if you look at
the number of of objects they are we
have in total yeah uh which is do you
remember how many object do we have yeah
uh so we have so in total we have like
7,500 objects uh I think roughly 15% of
them don't contain code at all so they
they also don't have events but that's
normal and then uh our events are
concentrated in about onethird of the
remaining objects M and then there's 50%
of the objects that could contain events
don't have events at all okay so I I
don't expect every object to get events
but it shows their very highly
concentrated um but that's to be
expected that's these are the places
where Partners need customization right
and there some some which are just you
know you don't want to customize I don't
know some basic things around there are
objects that don't need that don't need
uh customization there are others that
need a lot um I I get a little bit
scared sometimes when you see these uh
the the big objects sales posting
purchase posting and do have a lot of
events they have 600 plus events per
object or something no in the one in
sales most in code unit there's like 600
events so it becomes very difficult to
know exactly which event you should use
for your feature because you could pick
25 of them and it probably all work also
looked a little bit at how densely
populated an object is with uh with
events and we have objects where there
is an event for every five lines of code
so why is that why why is this a problem
have many events um because you you know
seem to indicate that it is is not a
good thing I don't think it's a it's a
good thing in principle there's nothing
wrong with having the events because if
you don't subscribe to them the
performance impact things like that
should be minimal but when we want to
make even something as simple as a bug
fix right around where these events are
or you want to refactor the code almost
every change you make in these objects
becomes breaking because you change
either the context in which the event is
raised you might change some of its
parameters you might um you might stop
calling the event you you know the event
might move somewhere else and so so if
you have an event every five line of
cude let's say you want to fix some bugs
in some procedure or something and if
you have an event every F and course
become very hard to it's kind of a
mindfield you you don't know where where
to change the code without you need to
respect the event if you really truly
want to be non-breaking you would need
to respect the order of which the events
are fired and all these things right so
so a big uh issue there is we are a
little bit blind to what uh our partners
do in in the subscribers to these events
M so we have a pretty good idea of what
what we of what you could use those
events for but we don't actually know
what they're doing so uh even though we
don't get we don't make compiler
breaking changes I mean the the partner
code will still compile and run but we
introduce side effect the behavior
changes the the expectation sometimes
changes so maybe we'll be a little bit
too generous with events but uh you but
I think maybe a compromise to I mean
what we wanted back back then what we
wanted was to accelerate the move of our
partners to the cloud so they they
wanted to be able to extend BC and get
to the class so we had to be a bit maybe
a bit generous with how many events we
we we uh we we implemented and give and
gave our partners but maybe now it's
time to to go back on this and and and
do a little bit of cleanup right yeah so
I mean it was absolutely necessary we
would not be where we are today if we
had not provided all the events that our
partners need um I think you know yes it
is time to take a more critical look at
at these events um so for example these
3,000 plus events that are not used in
the cloud um we we could choose to
remove those um so we can tell Partners
R we are going to remove some events you
know it's coming um I I think there's
other situations where if you look at um
a little bit of code maybe 25 lines of
code and there's three function calls
you get kind of like duplicate events
right so I might have an on before I
call this function event but then inside
that function I have another on before I
do this thing event so why do we need
both can we can we look at that and pick
one and then have that one um of course
get when I look at some of the names of
the events we have they also a little
bit telling you know how you like it's
not you some of them are called
something like on before this but after
that yes which you know which is a
little bit starts being a little bit
suspicious because it means that you you
want to do something you know basically
you want to uh intervene with your code
in between some other lines of code and
it starts to resemble very much uh the
go good old code customization model
right yeah I think I think right now we
have uh quite a lot of code where the
events are just
U glorified code customization right if
you if you have you know one or two
lines of code between two events we need
to find better ways of of handling that
I mean you say ultimately if we had an
event you know before and after each
line of code then we will be back to
code cation actually yeah I think so
which we don't have that yet yet and we
we hopefully we never will but uh I
think the the the the real issue behind
all of this is that we you know we we
went away from the code merges because
every time we changed our code and
partners had to merge that was
essentially a breaking change for them
whereas now we have so many events every
every time we make a change we're also
breaking our partners so we are
reintroducing this workload but in a
slightly different way it's no more text
merged but now it's you know they have
to rewrite their subscribers in a
different way and so that's that's also
um very painful it's so one last thing
that I wanted to mention about these
events because you mentioned the on
before on after so um we we tend to
think of the the very beginning of a
procedure or the very end of a procedure
As Natural places to to extend or to put
an event to extend code right so on
before would be the beginning and on
after would be after I did the thing so
looking at where our events are placed
in code we very much prefer the on after
um so about onethird of all events are
um on at the end of a function why is
that why do you prefer the on after I
don't know I think it's you mean when
you mean we prefer that there there are
more events which are on after after is
that what you mean so all Partners
actually prefer most that's what you
want to say right so I I think it's also
because you want to as a partner you
extend a feature you kind of think okay
after Microsoft has done this bit of
logic I want to inject my logic so at
the end of the function is is when when
that happens yeah yeah nothing wrong
with that um you also might want to do
something before like before Microsoft
processes this record I want to inject
my logic so that's fine so with the
beginning of the function it's a little
bit more spread out but again it's about
1/3 and then the rest of events so
that's 1/3 so that's 7,000 something
events they are really everywhere in the
code they're in the middle there are you
know uh and those are the ones that are
hardest to handle when you refactor code
because an event at the end you can you
can manage you can you can move it a
little bit more easily but if it's in
the middle of processing a particular
bit of logic it's very tricky to to
refactor and not break what the event
does so events events is is one
mechanism of extensibility it's not the
only one we have others right and uh so
what are the other um so let's you know
just up what how can you so if you if
you want to extend business Central when
you start Co you can subscribe to to
event that's one thing what else uh so
the the the most basic ones are uh
extensibility objects so page extension
table extension now report extension
they're kind of like the
big existing object you can add extra
fields to a table to a page um we have
we can extend enums now which are useful
in the code uh interfaces are a very
nice way of doing extensibility where a
partner can um either you know come with
their own implementation if we if we
allow them to to change the default
implementation then they can bring their
own that's I think that's very powerful
um so would you say interface a better
extensibility mechanism than as a as as
events it's two events it depends on the
situation I think um but yes I think in
in in many cases having an extensible
enum with an interface is a better way
of having the partner
provide their different implementation
in instead of what what we tend to do in
many places now is what we call a
handled event MH which is uh you
subscribe to it and you say I want to
skip this code that Microsoft did and
I'm going to put in my own
implementation yeah um and that that's
not a very friendly way of of extending
um interface are maybe a little more
clear of a contract it's a clear
confront an interface is is a much more
controlled way of doing things so do you
see us moving toward in that direction
having more and more interfaces and
extensible enms and less and less events
in the future I think as we as we
refactor the the Legacy B app code that
that's where we're going so when we look
at the the newer features that are being
written or the areas that we
componentize we see uh a heavy use of
interfaces in most old and new features
introduce some kind of interfaces um and
we see 10 times less events M so a
factor 10 less is is quite important and
it's not so much because we use
interfaces or because we pick one method
over
another I think it's more the the the
Legacy codebase was written for a code
customization model that that was the
purpose of it so it was written a
certain way when we now refactor the
code and we design it to be extensible
and and we
you know we we we do it on on purpose so
to say we design the feature to be
extended in a certain way through
interfaces with or without events we see
that we get far far fewer events um and
and we don't get the events that are
like code customization right you don't
get an event like between line seven and
eight you something you get much more
purposeful events you know and those are
much better and they don't change as
frequently so I think that's that is a
better model so talking about
refactoring let's uh let's let's talk a
little bit about the componentization
you've been working on componentization
for a while a long time now yeah for a
long time now so so uh yeah just give up
give us a little bit of a summary of
what where we at with that uh and so why
are we doing this you know what's what
is what is the good thing and uh what's
you know what what what have we done so
far and where are we going with this our
our Legacy base app is filled with um
it's basically spaghetti code right it's
got circular references everywhere it's
mostly very old code everything relies
on everything else and it's it's very
difficult to if you're a new developer
it's very difficult to understand why
things are the way they are it's not
documented because that was not required
in the past um and you it's it's there
you you can't really get an overview of
it so we we've done several things to
reduce the spaghetti code and turn it
into more reusable building blocks um so
uh we we are taking local features and
turning those into apps so that uh we
delocalize the base application mhm um
so that's at the top of the stat that's
at the top of the stack and that doesn't
really reduce Bap a lot because it's
it's mostly in the local versions but
those are the ones our partners use so
it's not without its Merit but it
doesn't do much for W1 MH um another
thing which which we we did a couple of
years ago was uh we started pulling fat
from the bottom mhm so that's very early
on started with splitting uh our
two-tier architecture into a three tier
right we split um the the server out and
we we took out that was a long time ago
old Cod unit one went away very long
time ago um but system application is
the step that came after that which is
why we don't have a code unit one today
yes that is that is true um so the
system application is all of these
utility type functionalities that are um
almost platform like but were built in
the appli
M um but they don't have so correct me
if I'm wrong but everything in a system
app has nothing to do withp actually no
more AP for yeah it's very technical
stuff HTTP requests Azure key Vols uh
things file IO all this kind of thing
which uh which don't really have
anything to do
uhp that's a requirement for being in
the system application is that it's it's
non business business domain stuff right
it's it's stuff that everybody will need
when writing almost any software program
mhm um and it's it's very close to the
platform so we we can seal it off a bit
better MH uh and we've we've made the
features extensible it's also open
source truly open source now it's it's
on GitHub and it's actually a different
app like also physically it's a
different extension right yeah Y and the
way we the way it's built is also
different so system application is one
app but it's actually made up of over a
hundred modules now which are each
individually built as an app as well we
that's just not the way we ship it but
we build it and test all of them
individually and then we repackage it as
one app and that's the one that we ship
so we actually what you're saying that
internally we actually building each of
these module as a separate extension a
separate app as a it's only a build
exercise right just a way to verify that
we have good separation of concern and
no circular dependen circular
dependencies so we could potentially
ship them yes uh but it's just a
physical the system app is just a
physical packaging all just more
convenient right to ship them together
and version it potentially we could uh
ship all of these modules in
individually right yeah I think the
decision to to not ship them
individually I think is more of a user
friendliness kind of thing like who
wants to manage 100 separate
dependencies when it's not really needed
to you have this this module in that
version and also from versioning
standpoint it's a little bit easier but
so who knows maybe one day you know that
will become a thing but so far you know
we the system app we call that a layer
um so it's a nice and easy way of
working it and we have the build system
to you know keep us honest so that we we
don't we don't mess up with the
dependency tree um so that that's very
good recently we added the next layer so
that that I think version 24 yeah Tre
ship 6 months ago yeah um we added
business Foundation MH so you've been
working a lot on that part yeah as well
so that is now the first time where
we're getting into the business domain
mhm so the the the rule so where system
application is you know no business
domain business Foundation is meant to
be the the foundational layer so the
rule there is it it there are features
that apply to none of the none of really
none of the domains but they're still
businesslike or all of them so it's it's
still so it has it is Erp related yeah
uh but it's not it's not Finance
specific Finance it's not inventory it's
not service
management but it is it is as opposed to
system you wouldn't find that type of
implementation in a in another in a nonp
software okay what are examples of
things in a business Foundation ler so
right now we have uh number
series um and audit codes kind of for
auto Trail um other candidates would be
things like like Dimensions
which it is a finance feature but it's
used everywhere basically everywhere um
so the work there would be so that maybe
if let's assume that's our next step
right so what so you would be the work
would be pulling everything that has to
do with Dimensions which today is in in
the B app right yeah and put it it in
factor factoring it out into into the
business foundation so there there's a
there's a couple of steps into doing
that so what would go in the business
Foundation is the really the core of
Dimensions right so think uh setups uh
actually the tables holding the
dimensions some of the basic logic
around Dimensions which you can you know
which combinations of Dimensions you can
use uh those kind of things that because
every other feature in in BC would use
that module and they might add features
to it or they might extend it or they
might use it in a slightly different way
but the core of it that would go into
business foundation and then everything
else is now becomes a user of that
module so that's that's I think number
series is a good a good way
to to to see what what that means when
we build these modules we actually we
rewrite most of the code um so we we we
don't just blindly take a feature copy
paste it somewhat and then say all right
now we made a module we actually we go
in and we we we try and rewrite the code
with modern tools um maybe fix some
issues that were in the original design
um improve the the feature if we see
things that that don't really work the
way we like um so yeah a lot of work
goes in also very important we document
everything that the public API uh gets
split out to separate objects so they're
they're easier to to handle and we
document all of those and and this
document get published also online right
it's not only so we have code comments
yeah it's it's in the code but it also
get published on the ma of it's
developer code and it gets extracted and
put in the developer section on on I
guess it's learning yeah we'll put some
links in the in the description yeah
yeah um so so so just to summarize so we
have we have have a a bottom up approach
where we take things like system app and
and uh and and business Foundation uh
and kind of you know put them at the
bottom of the stack in like separate
modules by the way is the business
Foundation is that also a separate app
yes it's also a layer app so we made up
of different modules but it's built and
shipped the same with the same process
as system application okay so it's also
a separate app it's a separate extension
so when you look at your extension
overiew in BC you'll see as a separate
one and then then we have a a top top
down you talk about localization we have
also did we do we also have other first
party apps at the at the top of the
stack also that we kind of you know
remove refactor factor out of B apps so
we do a lot of different things at same
um so we we build a lot of new new
features as apps that go on top um in
terms of componentized Base app we have
uh pulling out from the bottom the
localizations pulling out from the top
and now we're also looking at taking um
domains really so service management
manufacturing um taking those features
and putting putting those into a
separate app MH so that that will have a
big impact on on the base application
because it's it's a lot of code that
will get moved and we're still looking
into how we can make that non-breaking
and again this is all good because when
we do that you you make sure that for
example in in the in this module for
service management you don't we don't
have object which for examp are about
Finance or you know HR or some some
totally other you know area so that's
making sure we have a good separation of
concern and also when we create when we
create new objects then if if we kind of
um um have these modules which have a
clear defined purpose and role then we
know where to put them you know if we
okay you create a has to do with Finance
okay that goes there it goes with
something with HR okay that's goes there
right so in the future it's all good way
it's good to have these structure in
order to you know get more even more
structure yeah we we in the past the
whole application was one just put it on
something new you just put it on top of
the pile right it was very easy for the
developer you didn't have to think about
any of these things you just put it in
and and and that was it
the part was not easy maybe for new
developers to understand the app because
it was so unstructured it's still today
it's it's a pretty complex app right and
and what we hope also is with this
effort that eventually for new
developers or
even even season developers it would be
easier to navigate the app and
understand where where they need to it
needs to be extended uh and what it does
and and all this right y so we we we've
gone through several steps I think so
the first one of the first things we did
was we we uh organized our source code
into uh separate folders I think that
was one of the first things we did um we
introduced Nam spaces yeah so we uh even
though we still have the folder
structure we added name spaces to the
objects as a language a language feature
absolutely so so now it's much easier in
the code you can instantly see oh it
belongs to this area or that area and
this object while belonging to finance
actually relies on these other name
spaces and that's so now that we have
completion and in sense in in in Visual
Studio code it also help discoverability
of object the name space because you can
go and type uh you know Microsoft dot uh
and then Finance for example uh and then
Dot and then you will see a list of
objects which is much smaller than
before we had Nam space you would have
we also had intell sense and completion
and all that but you would have like a
very big list of all the tables and all
the you know which makes it a lot more
difficult to to find your way around
when you when you C absolutely we're
doing a lot of things to help
um reduce the amount of code you have to
sift through to understand the
functionality that you're working with
there isn't a single you know Magic
Bullet that will fix all of it but all
of these together I think make it uh
very useful also for componentization we
use name spaces to to figure out where
the limits of features are and we do
internal refactoring even though we
don't extract something as a component
we're already refactoring to make the
how do you say the namespace cloud you
know uh less of a mess but make it more
streamlined because that helps us later
so we're doing a lot of things in that
area so are this change are this Chang
are
breaking yes unfortunately many of them
are all of them um I wouldn't say all of
them but I think many of the changes
that we make end up being breaking so uh
again when we introduced the system
application at same time we introduced
an obso scheme MH so uh in the past a
new version would come out and partners
would discover like hey this this new
stuff broke my my functionality and I
have to rework everything and where I
start um now that we have these obso
properties we we obsolete code um we
give Partners I think 12 to 18 months to
to uptake so they get warnings so if
they recompile their app they can see
like oh this is going to be a problem
the code is still there yeah and then
and then after 18 months we actually
remove the old code and at that point it
does become breaking um we have very
strict guidelines around this we we do
try to avoid major breaking
changes um we provide Absolution you
know whenever we can MH but uh but yeah
it's I mean eventually if we need to
refactor we need to make some changes
which are breaking right yeah so um what
about pragmas and OBS and Absolution
obsolete code so uh there's a couple of
things let's talk a bit about that I
know it's something that's close to your
heart so uh it's so we when we started
with these obols MH uh very quickly we
realized that you know we were doing a
lot of it and at some point we were
going to have to clean this up and we
were actually building a mountain of
debt ahead of us that we could see
growing and you know because we weren't
actually removing it or no because we
were obsoleting knowing that you know in
two versions we're going to have to
remove this
had all these and remove that code so
that's when we started uh using the
pre-processor symbols MH um so we can
it's it's very useful compiler tool
right so we we add these uh symbols so
we can we can at the time of absolution
say you know this is the old code and
when we clean it up this is what the new
code is going to look like without
actually removing it but compile and the
compiler look at it as as if it was
removed right and and so we compile our
app in two ways so we compile with the
old code that's currently being shipped
and we also compile a version with you
know the the pre-processor symbols
enabled so that's the new code and we
make sure that both work MH so that that
removes a lot of the debt right because
we do it at the moment of absolution we
don't push it in front of it but then we
also have an automated process that par
the source code and removes the old code
so that's done automatically so it's
it's done automatically so we're we're
no longer pushing this mountain of debt
ahead of us we we I you know we operate
on a zero debt principle so if you if
you want to change some code today you
have to make sure that when you check
that in there is no extra work after two
years from now that everybody will have
forgotten about so um the the next step
in that story which is uh so we
obsoleted tables and Fields on uh on
which relates to the SQL schema M and um
we we couldn't change the SQL schema so
that was fine right they would just live
on forever but now a couple of years
later we have way too many of them and
it's starting to clutter the code so
we've decided that every fifth release
we're going to clean up the SQL schema
mhm
so that's good we can go do that but we
don't want every every two years or
something like that two and a half years
two and yeah so if I if we removed the a
field in in this release we don't want
to delete it the next release right so
we we need to know you know have these
fields been removed long enough M and so
now again we have the same situation
where we have this debt because we have
fields that were obsoleted in version 15
that are still there but we also have
fields obsoleted in version 25 and we
don't want to remove those yet so we
we're now introducing uh a new
pre-processor symbol which you call
clean
schema which um is so we add those
symbols so that we can use the same
automated process to clean this up and
the Deb we have is we have to go add all
these symbols to where we have these
removed TBL we didn't do it from the
beginning exactly yeah so uh you know we
we learn as we go then we fix it so in
version 26 now that we're working on
right now we will do this cleanup MH and
from then on it'll be an automated
process and so Partners will know
several releases ahead of time like hey
you know this field that they stopped
using it's actually going away in a
couple of releases so what do you say
the end goal is with this all compiz
eort what you know when uh I don't want
to ask when we'll be done because would
be bit hard to say but what's what's the
end goal um so uh
um
componentization it has many different
aspects right so the the we want uh
smaller apps that are that have one
purpose because they're easier to
understand they're easier to use we
document them so that you know Partners
don't have to know 6,000 objects they
can they can look at the API of a module
know what it does know what it's used
for and know how to use it so we want to
do that for all of our
code also at some point
you know once everything is
componentized I think it would be very
nice if we could have the components
actually be
replaceable so that Partners come in
with their own version of a given
component and just swap it out M we're
not there yet so we could have their own
HR module for example or you know that
would be I don't think anybody is going
to replace the finance
module I don't know I I that seems
ambitious but okay why not sorry
um long long long very long term you
know we are part of the the bigger
Dynamics family right and we have you
know Dynamics for sales we have finance
app we have you know operations app
so I I you know you might have companies
that are very heavily Finance focused
that might need a very heavy Finance
operations kind of you know deal there
but they they don't need very much of
the others and maybe BC is a better fit
M I think it's more common to be the
other way around you use BC for finance
and then have a you know dynamic sales
right and that if it was truly modular
and we could combine those in a distant
future I think that would be truly
powerful well maybe also we could maybe
there's a future where we could um not
install all these modules uh more lean
apps so like if you specific
installation at a specific customer if
they don't need a Char module inventory
module or Supply Chain management you
know pick pick your combination you
would only install the modules that that
that you need and then you know all the
events don't get fired you know probably
I'm not I'm not saying we would get
better performance but we will get
certainly you know reduced footprint in
terms of memory and and it would be very
good on many levels um so users wouldn't
see actions or pages that they don't
need that they don't use the UI would be
leaner as well yeah the UI would be
leaner um there will be less code to run
less code to manage so I I think it
would be very good in in many different
ways also uh um Partners wouldn't have
to consider so many side effects if they
knew like hey for this customer they're
only going to have these features
installed you no longer need to worry
about the others whereas now now those
features are there their code does
interact so so you you know you do need
to worry what the side effects is going
to be on those features even though the
customer is not going to use them so I I
think that would be very nice yeah all
right well that's a I think good
conclusion well um that's what a little
bit about our our our app and uh the
architecture of it um and I hope you
enjoy this episode thank you for
watching